Leroi Jones (Amiri Baraka) Collection
Leroi Jones (Amiri Baraka) Collection
1957-1968
Baraka, Amiri, 1934-2014.
2.5 linear ft.
Papers of the African-American author, music critic, novelist, playwright, poet, and social activist. Baraka was also editor of Yugen, a literary magazine, and co-editor, with Diane Di Prima, of The floating bear. Correspondence (1958-1965); Baraka's typescript and published writings, including articles, book manuscripts, book and music reviews, essays, playscripts, and poems; and Yugen records, including manuscripts and page proofs. Yugen manuscripts include those of John Ashbery, Paul Blackburn, Robin Blaser, Bruce Boyd, William Burroughs, Paul Carroll, Gregory Corso, Robert Creeley, Edward Dahlberg, Diane Di Prima, Edward Dorn, Larry Eigner, Allen Ginsberg, Barbara Guest, Stephen Jonas, Jack Kerouac, Kenneth Koch, Philip Lamantia, Ron Loewinsohn, Walter Lowenfels, Michael McClure, Edward Marshall, David Meltzer, Frank O'Hara, Charles Olson, Joel Oppenheimer, Stuart Perkoff, Gary Snyder, Gilbert Sorrentino, George Stanley, Philip Whalen, John Wieners, and William Carlos Williams.
149091
Biographical History
Everett LeRoi Jones was born on October 7, 1934 in Newark, New Jersey, the son of Coyette LeRoi and Anna Russ Jones. In his youth he showed considerable aptitude as a student, graduating from high school two years ahead of his class. Jones received a B.A. from Howard University in 1953, and spent the following two years in the United States Air Force.
Jones then settled in New York City and did graduate work in comparative literature at Columbia. He began to develop his talents as a poet and critic, becoming associated with what was known as the "Beat Generation" in the East Village. There Jones edited Yugen, a magazine of underground poetry, and co-edited a literary newsletter, the Floating Bear. With other poets, including Diane Di Prima, he founded the American Theatre for Poets, an avant garde Village dramatic group, in 1961. Jones read his verse in coffeehouses, and two volumes of his poems, Preface to a Twenty Volume Suicide Note and The Dead Lecturer, were published.
After a visit to Cuba in 1960, Jones began to condemn American culture, seeing American blacks as its victims. This theme was elaborated in his book Blues People: Negro Music in White America, published in 1963.
Jones' debut as a professional off-Broadway playwright came in 1964 with Dutchman, a shocking drama of interracial hostility. It ran for nearly a year in New York and was also presented abroad. Two more of his plays presented the following season, The Toilet and The Slave, were less successful.
In the mid-1960's LeRoi Jones wrote The System of Dante's Hell, an autobiographical novel, as well as Home: Social Essays and Tales. In 1965 he moved to Harlem where he founded the Black Arts Repertory Theatre. The following year Jones returned to Newark, N.J. and began "Spirit House", a multi-faceted black cultural workshop similar to his previous program in Harlem. In Newark he founded the Black Community Development and Defense Organization (BCD), a group of men and women dedicated to the "creation of a new value system for the Afro-American community", with stress placed upon elements of African culture. The group is of the Muslim faith and Jones now uses his Muslim name, Ameer Baraka. He has recently written several one-act plays for black audiences, including Slave Ship, Resurrection in Life, Great Goodness for Life (A Coon Show), Arm Yourself or Harm Yourself, and A Recent Killing. Jones occupies a position of political leadership in the black communities of Newark.
Jones' first marriage was to Hettie Cohen, his co-editor of Yugen. They had two children. He now lives at Spirit House with his second wife, Amini, their son, Ras Jua Al Aziz, and Mrs. Baraka's three daughters by a previous marriage.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Leroi Jones (Amiri Baraka) Collection consist of the personal, literary and publishing records of LeRoi Jones, an American poet, playwright and black separatist leader. The materials have been organized into four sections: Correspondence, Memorabilia, Writings and Yugen magazine records.
Correspondence is primarily incoming and relate to Jones' literary, political and personal concerns. The 1967-1968 correspondence pertains to the arrest of Jones and others during protests at the site of the Kawaida Towers housing project in Newark, New Jersey.
Memorabilia includes a calendar, a collage, newspaper clippings, printed matter, publisher's flyers, photographs, programs, and material related to the Casa de las Americas and the Fair Play for Cuba Committee. Of particular interest in this series is a portrait print of Jones by New York School artist Larry Rivers, signed by both Rivers and Jones.
Writings contains works by Jones and others. Jones' works include articles and essays, fiction and nonfiction books, book reviews, introductions, music reviews, plays, short stories and verse. The materials are in various stages of draft as well as in the final published versions. Works by other authors include reviews of Jones' books by Ralph Ellison and Phillip Roth.
Yugen magazine records consist of material related to the literary magazine of which Jones was the editor. Included here are authors' manuscripts, dummies, page proofs, promotional and published versions of the periodical. The authors' manuscripts, which include verse, plays and prose submitted by various noted writers, include Allen Ginsberg, Diane Di Prima, Jack Kerouac, and William S. Burroughs.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Memorabilia is arranged alphabetically by type. Writings are arranged alphabetically first by author, then by type of work and finally by title. Yugen records are organized first by the number of the issue, then by the type of material.
Subject and Genre Headings
African Americans; Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Radicalism; Ashbery, John, 1927-2017.; Baraka, Amiri, 1934-2014.; Blackburn, Paul, 1926-1971.; Blaser, Robin.; Boyd, Bruce.; Burroughs, William S., 1914-1997.; Carroll, Paul.; Corso, Gregory.; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005.; Dahlberg, Edward, 1900-1977.; Di Prima, Diane.; Dorn, Edward.; Eigner, Larry, 1927-1996.; Ginsberg, Allen, 1926-1997.; Guest, Barbara.; Jonas, Stephen.; Kerouac, Jack, 1922-1969.; Koch, Kenneth, 1925-2002.; Lamantia, Philip, 1927-2005.; Loewinsohn, Ron; Lowenfels, Walter, 1897-1976.; McClure, Michael.; Marshall, Edward, 1932-; Meltzer, David.; O'Hara, Frank, 1926-1966.; Olson, Charles, 1910-1970.; Oppenheimer, Joel.; Perkoff, Stuart Z.; Rivers, Larry, 1925-2002.; Snyder, Gary.; Sorrentino, Gilbert.; Stanley, George, 1934-; Whalen, Philip.; Wieners, John, 1934-2002.; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963.; Yugen.; African American dramatists.; African American novelists.; African American poets.; African Americans -- Biography.; American literature -- 20th century.; American literature -- African American authors.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Bohemianism.; Literature, Experimental.; Muslims, Black -- Biography.; Periodical editors -- United States.; Periodicals -- Publishing -- United States.; Articles.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Essays.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Poems.; Scripts (documents); Authors.; Editors.; Novelists.; Playwrights.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, various years.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1958-1965; 1967-1968,; undated; 7 folders (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Calendar, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Casa de las Americas, 1960-1962 (Box 1)
  - Collage, undated (Box 1)
  - Fair Play for Cuba Committee, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1958-1961 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, ca. 1960 (Box 1)
  - Printed material
    - "In-Formation," pre-publication issue, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Portrait print by Larry Rivers, signed by Rivers and Jones, 1966; reprint of a 1964 original (Box 1)
    - Revolution, Vol. II no. 1, Sept/Oct. 1964 (Box 1)
  - Programs and posters, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Publisher's flyers, 1960 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Ellison, Ralph
    - Book review, "Blues People by LeRoi Jones," New York Review of Books, I, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Jones, LeRoi
    - Miscellaneous fragments, undated (Box 1)
    - Articles, essays, statements
      - "Apple Cores", undated; typescript, revised (Box 1)
      - "The Black Man Has No Other Choice," Progressive Labor, III, 1964; published material (Box 1)
      - "Black Writing," American Dialog, I, 1964; published material (Box 1)
      - "In the Ring (2)," The Nation, 1964; published material (Box 1)
      - On Jack Kerouac, undated; typescript, revised (Box 1)
      - "The Largest Ocean in the World," Yugen 8, 1962 (Box 1)
      - "The Myth of 'Negro' Literature," Saturday Review, XLVI, 1963; published material (Box 1)
      - "The Need for a Rainbow Agenda", [1984?]; handwritten draft, heavily revised; evidently written around the time of the Democratic National Convention, as it mentions candidacy of Jesse Jackson and the need for a "revolutionary Democratic agenda" (Box 1)
      - "Nick Charles Meets the Wolfman", undated; typescript carbon (Box 1)
      - "Note on One Side (The Study)", undated; typescript, revised (Box 1)
      - "Putdown of the Whore of Babylon", undated; typescript, revised (Box 1)
      - "re The South", undated; typescript, revised (Box 1)
      - Statement by Jones regarding his arrest during the Kawaida Towers protests, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
      - "The Task of the Negro Writer as Artist," Negro Digest, XIV, 1965 (Box 1)
      - "This Pleasant and Affable Young Man Has a Message for You," Cavalier, XVI, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Books, fiction
      - The System of Dante's Hell
        - Draft, typescript carbon, undated (Box 1)
        - Published edition, Grove Press, New York, 1963, Sent to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - Books, non-fiction
      - Blues People: Negro Music in White America
        - Draft typescript, revised, pp. 1-129, undated (Box 1)
        - Draft typescript, revised, pp. 130-287, undated (Box 2)
        - Galley proofs, revised, 1963; 2 folders (Box 2)
      - "Cuba Libre"
        - Draft typescript, revised, undated (Box 2)
        - Galley proofs, revised, undated (Box 2)
    - Book reviews
      - The Art of Jazz, ed. by Martin T. Williams, undated (Box 2)
        Jazz, ed. by Nat Hentoff and Albert J. McCarthy; The Collector's Jazz--Modern, by John S. Wilson; The Sound of Surprise, by Whitney Balliett, ts rev
      - "New Books of Poetry", ca. 1960; typescript, revised (Box 2)
    - Introductions
      - The Moderns, an Anthology of New Writing in America
        - Promotional material, 1963 (Box 2)
        - Published edition, Corinth Books, New York, 1963, Sent to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
    - Music reviews
      - Fragments, 1958 (Box 2)
      - "The Avant Garde", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - "Blue Gator--Willis Jackson", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Bop and Avant Garde Compositions", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - "Brownie McGhee", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - "Capuchin Swing", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Coltrane", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - "Gene Ammons: Boss Tenor", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "James Waring and Dance Company", 1962; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - On Jazz, undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Jazz as Satire and Ridicule (from an Essay in Progress)", undated; note and holo. (Box 2)
      - On John Coltrane, Cecil Taylor and Art Blakely at Lincoln Center, undated; galley proof (Box 2)
      - "Junior Mance", undated; ts. (Box 2)
      - "Lonnie Johnson and Elmer Snowden", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - "Moody's Workshop", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Mucho, Mucho--Shirley Scott with the Latin Jazz Quintet", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Muddy Waters", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - "Oliver Nelson, Eric Dolphy, Richard Williams", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
      - "Prestige 7178--Bacalao", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "The Rocking Fifties", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Rocky Boyd", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Soul Time: Bobby Timmons", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "South Side Soul--The John Wright Trio", undated; typescript carbon (Box 2)
      - "Who is Miles Davis", undated; typescript, revised (Box 2)
    - Plays
      - The Baptism, undated; typescript reproduction, revised (Box 3)
      - Dutchman
        - Draft, revised, 1964; reproduction (Box 3)
        - Galley proofs, revised, 1964 (Box 3)
      - Dutchman and The Slave
        - Cover design, undated (Box 3)
        - Published edition, William Morrow and Co., New York, 1964, Sent to Rare Books for cataloging. Please refer to to locate this item.
      - "The Marathon Runner", undated; typescript, revised (Box 3)
      - "Riker's Morning", undated; typescript, revised (Box 3)
      - The Slave
        - Draft typescript, revised, undated (Box 3)
        - Galley proofs, revised, 1964 (Box 3)
      - The Toilet, undated; typescript, revised (Box 3)
    - Short stories
      - "The Alternative," The Transatlantic Review, 1965; published material (Box 3)
    - Verse
      - "The ABC's (For Charles)", undated; typescript, signed (Box 3)
      - "Citizen Cain" and "Theory," The Spero, Fenian Head Center Press, Flint, Michigan, 1965; published editions (Box 3)
      - "Crow Jane," Burning Deck, 1963; published editions (Box 3)
      - "Dialectic" and "An Execution," Helicon, III, 1964; published editions (Box 3)
      - "The Gift of the Universe," Epos, X, 1958; published editions (Box 3)
      - "Node", undated; typescript, signed (Box 3)
      - "Theory of Art," Provincetown Review, 1961; published editions (Box 3)
      - "Instruction for Negroes (a handbook of violence)", undated; typescript (Box 3)
      - "Like Rousseau", undated; typescript carbon (Box 3)
      - "The Disguise", 1961; published edition (Box 3)
      - "Spring and soforth", 1960; published edition (Box 3)
      - "Valery as Dictator," "The Liar," and "Snake Eyes," Poetry, CIII, 1963; published edition (Box 3)
    - Verse collections
      - The Dead Lecturer
        - Draft typescript, revised, undated (Box 3)
        - Galley proofs, revised, 1964 (Box 3)
        - Page proofs, 1964 (Box 3)
        - Published edition, Grove Press, New York, 1964 (Box 3)
      - Preface to a Twenty Volume Suicide Note
        - Draft typescript carbon, 1957-1960 (Box 3)
        - Published edition, Totem Press/Corinth Books New York, 1961 (Box 3)
    - Verse set to music
      - "The Turncoat" score, 1961 (Oversize 1)
  - Jones, LeRoi and others
    - Interview, 1961 (Box 4)
  - Loewinsohn, Ron
    - Book review, fragment typescript, revised, undated (Box 4)
  - Nichols, Herbie
    - Verse collection, untitled, typescript carbon, undated (Box 4)
  - Roth, Phillip
    - Book reviews, 1964; Blues for Mr. Charlie, by James Baldwin" and "Dutchman, by LeRoi Jones," New York Review of Books, II (Box 4)
  - Sachs, Ed
    - Articles and essays, undated; "Some Problems of Jazz in Fiction," ts. annot. (Box 4)
  - Tatum, Marvin
    - Articles, 1961; "A Look at the American Small Press Today," Cornell Library News, X (Box 4)
  - Unidentified verse, undated (Box 4)
- Yugen magazine records
  - Miscellaneous
    - Authors' manuscripts, undated (Box 4)
    - Promotional material, 1959 (Box 4)
  - Yugen 2
    - Published material, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Yugen 5
    - Authors' manuscripts
      - Articles
        - Gilbert Sorrentino, "A Note on Gregory Corso's To Black Mountain" (Box 4)
      - Verse
        - Paul Blackburn, "Ramus, Divendres, Diumenga" and "A Purity Defined" (Box 4)
        - Gregory Corso, "Food" (Box 4)
        - Diane DiPrima, "Earthsong" (Box 4)
        - Larry Eigner, Untitled (Box 4)
        - Max Feinstein, "A Blue Whale's" (Box 4)
        - Rainer Gerhardt, "Fragment" and "Voices" (Box 4)
        - Allen Ginsberg, "Kaddish" (Box 4)
        - Barbara Guest, "Sunday Evening" and "The Crisis" (Box 4)
        - Jack Kerouac, "Sitting Under Tree Number Two" (Box 4)
        - Walter Lowenfels, "The Nightingale" (Box 4)
        - Michael McClure, "Rant Block" (Box 4)
        - David Meltzer, "15th Raga/ for Bela Lugosi" and "From Night Before Morning/ Book One" (Box 4)
        - Barbara Moraff, Untitled (Box 4)
        - Frank O'Hara, "Ode on Casuality" (Box 4)
        - Joel Oppenheimer, "The Issue at Hand" (Box 4)
        - Cesar Vallejo, "Black Stone on a White Stone" (Box 4)
        - Philip Whalen, "I Return to San Francisco" (Box 4)
        - John Wieners, "A Poem for Virgins" (Box 4)
        - William Carlos Williams, "A Formal Design" (Box 4)
    - Dummy (Box 4)
    - Promotional material (Box 4)
    - Published material, 1959; 2 copies (Box 4)
  - Yugen 6
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Authors' manuscripts
      - Articles
        - Edward Dahlberg, "On Passions and Asceticism" (Box 4)
      - Verse
        - Paul Blackburn, "Song of the Wires" (Box 4)
        - Robin Blaser, "Out to Dinner" (Box 4)
        - Ray Bremser, "Backyards and deviations" (Box 4)
        - Paul Carroll, "By Its Familiar Accent" We Recognize the Ghost" (Box 4)
        - Robert Creeley, "What's for Dinner" (Box 4)
        - Ed Dorn, "The 6th" and "The 7th" (Box 4)
        - Larry Eigner, Untitled (Box 4)
        - Jack Kerouac, "Rimbaud" (Box 4)
        - Kenneth Koch, "From a Book of Poetry" (Box 4)
        - Philip Lamantia, "Blank Poem for Poe" (Box 4)
        - Ron Loewinsohn, "Trees/ 6" and "Etude, with Chair" (Box 4)
        - Edward Marshall, Untitled (Box 4)
        - Michael McClure, "The Column" (Box 4)
        - David Meltzer, "4th Raga/ for John Kelly Reed" (Box 4)
        - Frank O'Hara, "Personal Poem" (Box 4)
        - Charles Olson, "As of Bozeman," "The Distances" and "Letter, May 2, 1959" (Box 4)
        - Rochelle Owens, "Groshl Monkeys Horses" (Box 4)
        - Gary Snyder, "A Walk," "Wild Horses," "afterwork" and "On Vulture Peak" (Box 4)
        - Tristan Tzara, trans. by Daisy Alban, "Wheat" (Box 4)
        - David Wang, "II. Invocation" (Box 4)
    - Published material, 1959; 2 copies (Box 4)
  - Yugen 7
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Authors' manuscripts
      - Articles
        - Robert Creeley, "The New World" (Box 4)
        - Larry Eigner, "Letter" (Box 4)
        - Frank O'Hara, "Personism: a Manifesto" (Box 4)
        - Joel Oppenheimer, letter (Box 4)
        - Gilbert Sorrentino, "Some Notes..." (Box 4)
      - Plays
        - Kenneth Koch, "Guinevere or the Death of the Kangaroo" (Box 4)
      - Verse
        - John Ashbery, "From a comic book" and "Leaving the Atucha Station" (Box 4)
        - Bruce Boyd, "Summer nightmusic," "This is how the wind sings, lover, on the beach," "A quarrel of minstrels,' "Water," "Song," "Poem" (Box 4)
        - Gregory Corso, "On Chessman's Crime" (Box 4)
        - Diane DiPrima, "The Jungle" (Box 4)
        - Larry Eigner, untitled (Box 4)
        - Max Feinstein, "For Fair Eleanor" (Box 4)
        - Allen Ginsberg, "The End" (Box 4)
        - Edward Marshall, "Sept. 1957" (Box 4)
        - Charles Olson, "Theory of Society" (Box 5)
        - Joel Oppenheimer, "Morning Song" (Box 5)
        - Stuart Z. Perkoff, "To Orpheus," "Poem" and "Pithecanthropus Erectus" (Box 5)
        - B. Smith, "Empty Bed Blues" (Box 5)
        - Philip Whalen, "Literary Life in the Golden West," "Sincerity Shot, 23:III:58" and "A Manuscript in Several Hands 3:III:60" (Box 5)
    - Published material, 1961; 2 copies (Box 5)
  - Yugen 8
    - Authors' manuscripts
      - Articles
        - Robert Creeley, "Some Notes on Olson's" (Box 5)
        - Gilbert Sorrentino, "Duncan and Spicer" (Box 5)
        - Gilbert Sorrentino, "2 Books" (Box 5)
        - George Stanley, "Finstein and Sorrentino" (Box 5)
      - Prose
        - Edward Dorn, "Notes About Working and Waiting Around" (Box 5)
      - Verse
        - William Burroughs, "The Cut Up Method" (Box 5)
        - Steve Jonas, "Tensone with Relent," "Discourse," "To a Strayed Cat" and "A Long Poem for Jack Spicer" (Box 5)
        - Edward Marshall, "Memory as Memorial in the Last" (Box 5)
        - Charles Olson, "Book ii Chapter 37" and "place; and names" (Box 5)
        - Gilbert Sorrentino, "The Meeting" and "The Memory" (Box 5)
        - Speckled Red, "Red's Dozens" (Box 5)
        - George Stanley, "The message held up to the speeding train on a willow hoop," "Punishment," "The meteor," "The implicit acknowledgements," "Valentine," "A false start" (Box 5)
    - Page proofs (Box 5)
    - Published material, 1962; 2 copies (Box 5)